בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's דף daf is ע"ב, Ayin Bais,
or דף daf we're doing today, 72,
and we are continuing to move through the משנה. Mishnah. And I
think you're starting to get a nice idea why they like doing
מרובה Mrubba in the ישיבות yeshivas because it's like it's one juicy
סוגיא sugya after another. So we just dealt with all these questions
about a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya, שוחטing shochet it and
then is it fit for consumption or not, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה,
kim leh b'derabba minei, שוחטing shochet it on שבת, Shabbos,
questions about when the thing is אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
when it's a שור הנסקל shor haniskal or שוחט shochet to עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, and that type of a
case. It's obviously, forget שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya, it's obviously
there'd be no payment because you're שוחטing shochet something that's worthless or
if it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah it's considered to be not owned
by the owners and so on. So now, within the, like, immediately
continuing in that context, the next line in the משנה Mishnah is
the שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya discussion. If something is שוחטed
shochet for חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah or שוחטed shochet and it's a
טריפה, treifa, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you're still חייב,
chayiv, you still did a שחיטה shechita on it, and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says that you are פטור pattur because this is a
שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya, it's a שחיטה shechita that cannot
be eaten. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
because once again we're going to have the problem: טריפה treifa is
fine, that makes sense, it can't be eaten but you can get
הנאה, hana'ah, but חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah should fall us, put us
back into that category of איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, something you can't
derive benefit from because we're going to presume that חולין בעזרה chullin
ba'azarah is forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. And therefore the question is going
to be: well, if it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya,
you know, when you by the, by the time you basically finish
שוחטing shochet it, it's, it's worthless, it's no longer the owner's, etc.
So why would anybody say you're חייב? chayiv? Let's take a look.
So it's four lines from the top on דף ע"ב עמוד א':
daf Ayin Bais amud aleph: השוחט ונמצא טריפה. Hashocheit ve'nimtza treifa. אמר
ליה רב
חביבא ממחוזנא לרב אשי: Amar leh Rav Chaviva michuzna l'Rav Ashi: רב
חביבא Rav Chaviva from מחוזנא Mchuozna said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
שמע מינה Shma mina we can infer from this משנה, Mishnah, אין
לה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף, ein lah l'shechita ela l'sof, that the act
of שחיטה shechita is considered to take place only at the last
minute. Okay, when you actually, like, you know, שחיטה shechita is the
cutting of the trachea and the esophagus, the majority of both. So
anything you do to get up to 49%, 50% of the cutting
of the trachea and the esophagus, that's not yet the act of
שחיטה. shechita. Okay, the act of שחיטה shechita is that last bit
going from 50% to 51%. All right. Now, even within saying it
like that, you know, you got to think about exactly how you
want to phrase it because if that's really true that you're only
considered to do a שחיטה shechita at that last bit, so then
why isn't everybody always שוחטing shochet a טריפה? treifa? Because by the
time you get to the 51%, the animal already has a cut
trachea and an esophagus and it's not going to live, so you
could say, well, you know, fine, that's the, that's the way it
gets done. But anyway, somehow we don't just say that you're defined
as doing the act of שחיטה shechita from the beginning. The act
of שחיטה shechita is the final bit that actually makes it שוחטed.
shochet Okay, that's אין לה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף. ein lah l'shechita ela
l'sof. So that's as opposed to ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshno
l'shechita mitichila v'ad sof. From the minute you begin cutting, we call
that the process
or the act of the שחיטה. shechita. To what difference does that
have? So כיוון דאין לה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף, keivan d'ein lah l'shechita
ela l'sof, דאי ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, de'i yeshno l'shechita mitichila
v'ad sof, if you say that it's considered שחיטה shechita from the
moment you begin שוחטing, shochet so כיון דשחט בה פורתא אסרה, keivan
d'shachat ba'purta assra, as soon as you began to שוחט shochet it,
you have now שוחטed shochet חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah.
When did you do an act of שחיטה shechita of חולין בעזרה?
chullin ba'azarah? So, right, that's what you're doing. So he says, well,
from the minute you began cutting. Now, of course תוספות Tosafot points
out, if you stopped in the middle before you got to the
end, retroactively you never would have done a שחיטה. shechita. You would
have just nicked the animal's neck, right? But if,
assuming you're going to complete it, then we will in hindsight say
the שחיטה shechita began from the beginning of the cutting. And therefore
from that beginning of the cutting, you are doing a שחיטה shechita
of חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah and that's the moment it became אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah from the time the act of שחיטה shechita began.
That's the assumption of ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshno l'shechita mitichila
v'ad sof. ואי סלקא דעתך ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, v'ei salka
da'atach yeshno l'shechita mitichila v'ad sof, כיון דשחט בה פורתא אסרה, keivan
d'shachat ba'purta assra, when you begin to שוחט shochet it, you've made
it forbidden as חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. אידך, idach, now as you
continue from going from 5% to 51%, so לאו דמרי קטבח, lav
d'mari katavach, you're שוחטing shochet something that's already אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah
and therefore is either considered not to belong to the owner or
to be, which is literally what the גמרא Gemara says, or to
be worthless, and therefore you are not חייב. chayiv. Okay. Now,
the obvious answer to this would be: one minute, if the act
of שחיטה shechita for חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah begins from the first
moment, let's say the act of שחיטה shechita for שחיטה shechita to
be חייב chayiv for four and five begins on the first moment,
right? So therefore from the moment you begin, you've made it חולין
בעזרה chullin ba'azarah and you've done a שחיטה shechita of something that
is considered to be the owners. Because let's imagine that you have,
what's the alternative? The alternative is אין לה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף. ein
lah l'shechita ela l'sof. So from going from 50% to 51%, that's
when you made it חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. Good. When did you
שחיטה, shechita, when were you חייב chayiv four and five? Also when
you went... from 50% to 51%. So if the חיוב chiyuv four
and five comes at the same time as it becomes אסור בהנאה,
assur behana'ah, you're still חייב. chayav. The only time you'd be פטור
patur is first it became אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and then you
did the שחיטה. shechitah. At that stage, you'd be exempt. Well, why
don't we say here they're also coming at the same time? The
act of making חולין בעזרה Chulin Ba'azarah begins at the beginning of
the act and the act of being חייב chayav four and five
begins at the beginning of the act. So that seems to be
like the obvious answer. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So
one minute, let's see the גמרא's Gemara answer. אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרבא, Amar lei Rav Acha brei de-Rava, no, כי קמחייב והוא
פורתא. ki kemichayav v'hu purta. No,
when you're חייב chayav four and five, you're also חייב chayav for
the beginning, the little beginning that you've done. So it's the same
story.
So אמר ליה רב אשי, amar lei Rav Ashi, so Rav Ashi
said, no, לא סדחי, lo sidchi, don't push that off, וטבחו כולה
בעינן וליכא. utvacho kulla ba'inan v'leika.
Somehow, because the פסוק pasuk says—I don't know why the גמרא Gemara
takes it so much for granted—but it doesn't say just the word
you שחט, shachat, but וטבחו. utvacho. I don't know if it's the
word טביחה tvichah as opposed to שחיטה shechitah or the ו, vav,
you shall שחט shacht it. Okay, so it means that the חיוב
chiyuv comes only when you fully שחט shacht it, which to a
certain degree makes sense because if you understand that part of the
problem here is it's not so much a ritual act is the
שחיטה shechitah vis-a-vis your חיוב chiyuv of four and five, but it's
the נשתנה בחטא נשתרש בחטא. nishtana be-chet nishtarash be-chet. So then to
some degree, right, you want to say that even if it's considered
to begin the act of שחיטה, shechitah, the חיוב chiyuv comes when
you have fully had the impact of your actions. Okay, so therefore,
no, the חיוב chiyuv comes at the end of the שחיטה. shechitah.
But if the process begins at the beginning, then you've made it
אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah before the person is חייב chayav and therefore
they should never be חייב. chayav. That's the question. Yes, Michael. Does
that also mean just if I say, let's say that ישנו לשחיטה
מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshno lishchitah mitechillah v'ad sof, that in the middle
of שחיטה shechitah then I can then מקדיש makdish it to God
and then it'd be good and be a good קרבן? korban? Can
I do that?
Well, that's an interesting question because again that raises the question about
something that became קדוש kadosh when it already had like—assuming that you
had begun it and like to the point like it was already
a טריפה—if treifah you were to stop here, would you already have
made it a טריפה? treifah? So like I don't know. I mean,
it's one thing to say that you know that like it's in
the middle and we don't consider it a טריפה treifah because it's
part of the process, but could you make it a קרבן korban
and change its status and whatever? Yeah, I don't know. That's an
interesting question. But I mean, maybe yes, but I, my gut is
that the answer is no because it's already a טריפה treifah from
that perspective, like from the perspective it begins as a קרבן, korban,
at this moment it already has a partially cut trachea. But I
do want to say as because you mentioned קדשים, kodashim, that רש״י
Rashi says another נפקא מינה nafka mina for this question is if
you remember in all of זבחים, Zevachim, the whole question is if
somebody שחט shacht a קרבן korban and has a thought to eat
it in the wrong place, at the wrong time, has a thought
of שלא לשמו. she-lo lishma. So רש״י Rashi says this question is
to define when is the time the person could have that thought,
right? If the person had that thought before the act began but
not when he got to the final cut—you know, it's not like
it's a separate cut, it has to be one movement—but not when
he got to the, you know, final part of going to 51%,
then it would not be a thought of פיגול, pigul, right, if
you say it's only בסוף. besof. But if it's מתחילה ועד סוף,
mitechillah v'ad sof, then any thought during that process would be a
thought to affect the status of the קרבן. korban. My question is
in terms of וטבחו. utvacho. I thought you said oh שחט shacht
and it's a טריפה, treifah, okay, maybe you are, maybe you aren't,
depending on if it's ישנו לשחיטה yeshno lishchitah or לא. lo. Would
it be the same thing if I just shot it? Yes, and
no. If you shot it and then for, yeah, we discussed that
before. If that's not שחיטה, shechitah, then that's like an act of
just killing it. So everybody agrees, forget רב, Rav, the שחיטה שאינה
ראויה, shechitah she-einah re'uyah, everybody agrees you're פטור patur in that case.
But if you say again if it's just weird, or נשתרש בחטא
nishtarash be-chet or, I understand, but the תורה Torah doesn't say if
you destroy it, the תורה Torah says if you sell it or
you שחט shacht it. Both of those are also not just ways
of hurting the owner, but of enriching yourself, so that's part of
the problem. But anyway, but yeah, so I mean if it was
not שחט ונעשה טריפה, shachat vena'asah treifah, but שחט ונבלה בידו, shachat
veniveilah beyado, you messed up in the שחיטה shechitah and you made
it a נבלה, neveilah, then everybody says you're פטור, patur, that's not
a מעשה שחיטה. ma'aseh shechitah. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara, that's, so
the גמרא Gemara still's got this problem. Your חיוב chiyuv four and
five comes at the end of the act, but if you made
it if the act of שחיטה shechitah is at the beginning and
you made it חולין בעזרה Chulin Ba'azarah in the beginning, then then
you're, it's already אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and you won't be חייב
chayav for the end of the act. So אלא קשיא, ela kashya,
so what are you going to do? So אמר ליה הכי אמר
רב גמדא משמיה דרבא, amar lei hachi amar Rav Gamda mishmei de-Rava,
כגון ששחט מקצת סימנים בחוץ וגמר בפנים. kegon she-shachat miktzat simanim bachutz
vegamar bifnim. Ah, that's clearly פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishna. So
how
you did it, you had the animal, yeah, you've got to imagine,
like you had the animal one step outside, right, here you know,
you know, here's the, here's the עזרה, azarah, okay, here's your animal,
okay, and you're שחט-ing shacht your animal here, here's your knife, okay,
anyway, you're שחט-ing shacht your animal, so you start it and maybe
you're walking with it because you remember if like you hesitate or
you stop and you start again, you פסול pasul the שחיטה. shechitah.
So anyway, maybe you're like walking with the animal, so you do
the first 49% or 50% outside the עזרה, azarah, so you haven't
yet made it חולין בעזרה, Chulin Ba'azarah, and then as you're getting
to 51%, you somehow you're walking together with it and you made
it חולין בעזרה, Chulin Ba'azarah, so the moment that you're חייב chayav
four and five is also the moment you made it. חולין בעזרה.
chullin ba'azarah. It's a pretty ridiculous description. The גמרא Gemara yesterday, you
remember, said that when you said that when you it was a
question of doing an act of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it said
that you said I'm only offering this up at the end of
the act. That you could say because you don't have to do
something physically weird, you just have to designate when are you intending
to offer to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But here it's a physical
question: when where was the animal when it was שחטed? shacht Was
it in the עזרה azarah or not? Okay, so that's what says
you were walking in as you basically were finishing the שחיטה. shechita.
Okay, איכא דמתני להא. Ika d'masnei loha. Some teach this debate; it
started from the other end, not from our משנה, mishna, but from
the debate about
what's the process of
שחיטה. shechita. אמר רבי שמעון משום דרבי לוי סבא, Amar Rabbi Shimon
mishum d'Rabbi Levi saba, Rabbi Shimon says in the name of Rabbi
Levi the elder, אינו לשחיטה אלא לבסוף, eino l'shechita ela l'sof, שחיטה
shechita is considered to occur at the last moment. רבי יוחנן אמר,
Rabbi Yochanan amar, ישנו לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshno l'shechita miteichila v'ad
sof. No, it's from the beginning to the end. אמר רב חביבי
מחוזנאה לרב אשי, Amar Rav Chavivi miChuzao l'Rav Ashi, so Rav Chavivi
from Chuzao said to Rav Ashi, לימא קסבר רבי יוחנן חולין שנשחטו
בעזרה לאו דאורייתא. leima kasavar Rabbi Yochanan chullin shenishchatu ba'azarah lav de'oraisa.
If the only way—wait a minute—if it's if it's from the beginning
to the end, the only way I can make sense of that
position because I'm going to because in terms of our משנה mishna
is that חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is לאו דאורייתא, lav de'oraisa, not
biblical. Now there's an interesting question: does that mean that there's no
biblical prohibition? Because you know the תורה Torah says like כי ירחק
ממך המקום ki yirchak mimcha hamakom if the place is distant from
you, you know, what's the פסוק pasuk Michael? כי ירחק ממך המקום
אשר ה' אלהיך יבוא ki yirchak mimcha hamakom asher Hashem Elokecha yavo
whatever. But
anyhow somehow I can't remember the פסוק pasuk at the top of
my head. Any help there? כי ירחק ממך המקום אשר ה' אלהיך
יבוא ki yirchak mimcha hamakom asher Hashem Elokecha yavo
anyhow. So somehow the פסוק pasuk says that when the place is
distant from you, you should slaughter your animals and eat them. So
the גמרא's Gemara דרשה drasha is בריחוק מקום אתה זובח ולא בקירוב
מקום אתה זובח. brikhuk makom ata zove'ach v'lo bekiruv makom ata zove'ach.
You can only שחט shacht non-קדשים kodshim animals outside, not close. But
that's like an inference. So when we say חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah
is לאו דאורייתא, lav de'oraisa, does that mean that it's really even
מן התורה min HaTorah מותר mutar to do? It never explicitly says
you're not allowed to שחט shacht חולין. chullin. Or the more common
understanding is no, no, no, everybody agrees מן התורה min HaTorah it's
אסור assur to שחט shacht חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. They agree to
that דרשה. drasha. The question is what's the status of the animal
if it were done? Like because there's certainly nothing in the פסוק
pasuk that says that the animal is אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So
he says the only way I'm going to explain this position of
ישנו לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף yeshno l'shechita miteichila v'ad sof is to
say that מן התורה min HaTorah the animal is not forbidden in
הנאה, hana'ah, okay, does not become forbidden. And then I will be
able to explain our משנה, mishna, right? Because then our—because again it's
the same problem. If the חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah begins at the
first second, how are you חייב chayav four and five by the
time you finish it? It's already אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So he
says, oh, I got an answer. The איסור הנאה issur hana'ah is
not from the תורה. Torah. And therefore since it's only
רבנן—rabbinic—it's rabbanan not going to get in the way of you being
חייב chayav four and five. Since through the תורה Torah lens, you're
still it still belongs to the owner, it's still מותר בהנאה. mutar
behana'ah. So as opposed to this weird answer of walking the animal
in—it's רבנן rabbanan four and five? It's a what? No, the opposite.
It's a biblical four and five. No, saying but can you even
say everything's—oh why don't you say that the rabbis making it אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah prevented you from paying four and five? You could
say that. So I was going to say it in a minute,
but I'll stop for a moment. תוספות Tosafos says wait one minute.
Does that mean that anytime something is אסור בהנאה מדרבנן, assur behana'ah
midrabbanan. it would not have this impact on four-five? We earlier discussed
bringing something as a תקרובת עבודה זרה tikroves avoda zara as an
offering to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And the גמרא Gemara said there
that that would stop you from being חייב chayav four and five
because you wouldn't be שחט shachting something that was belonged to the
owner, etc. תוספות Tosafos says, but wait one minute, there are some
opinions that that's only אסור בהנאה מדרבנן. assur behana'ah midrabbanan, So why,
you know, if we're saying we ignore the דרבנן derabbanan status, why
there are you פטור? patur? So תוספות Tosafos says, no, here's the
difference. There, whether it's דאורייתא de'oraisa or דרבנן, derabbanan, it's status. Everybody
agrees that the status is that it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah So
yes, it's not like we always bracket דרבנן, derabbanans, we live in
a world of דרבנן derabbanan realities. Why should we bracket the דרבנן
derabbanan reality? You know, it's like the גמרא Gemara says that if
somebody tries to marry a woman on ערב פסח Erev Pesach with
some חמץ chametz that's only אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah. מדרבנן, midrabbanan, the
woman is not married. We tend to, right? Because the rabbis sort
of define our reality. So sure, if it's אסור בהנאה דרבנן, assur
behana'ah derabbanan, if תקרובת עבודה זרה tikroves avoda zara is אסור בהנאה
דרבנן, assur behana'ah derabbanan, you're not חייב chayav four and five. But
what it means when you say that חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is
דרבנן derabbanan means if it's דרבנן derabbanan it means that you believe
the rabbis never made it forbidden בהנאה. behana'ah. Maybe they made it
forbidden באכילה, ba'achila, but they never made it forbidden בהנאה. behana'ah. So
say חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is דרבנן derabbanan is really a way
of saying it's not really אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, לא דאורייתא lo
de'oraisa and לא דרבנן. lo derabbanan. Okay, it's like so if you
want to see that in תוספות, Tosafos, okay, take a look at
תוספות Tosafos אי סלקא דעתך i salka da'atach because we have a
little extra time today given the size of the דף. daf. אי
סלקא דעתך מדאורייתא כי שחטיה פורסא, i salka da'atach mide'oraisa ki shachatei
pursa, תוספות Tosafos says, משמע דהוי—which mashma d'havei one? Very top of
ע"ב ע"ב. ayin beis amud beis. Oh,
okay. משמע דהוי מדרבנן חשיב דמרי שפיר, mashma d'havei midrabbanan chashiv d'mari
shapir, if it was only a rabbinic problem of אסור בהנאה, assur
behana'ah, it sounds like you would be חייב chayav four and five,
it would be considered belonging to the owners. ומתוכך היה נראה לדקדק,
umitocheich hayah nireh l'dakdeik, if that's true we could infer, שתקרובת עבודה
זרה אסור בהנאה דאורייתא, she'tikroves avoda zara assur behana'ah de'oraisa, that offerings
to עבודה זרה avoda zara are forbidden בהנאה דאורייתא behana'ah de'oraisa because
the גמרא... Gemara... said if it was a תקרובת עבודה זרה, tikrovet
avodah zarah, you wouldn't be חייב chayav four and five. מדקאמר לעיל
דרבי מאיר שקיל לעבודה זרה ומיחייב Mideka'amar le'il derabbi Meir shakil la'avodah
zarah umichayev etc. etc., so then תוספות Tosafot goes and he has
all these questions and in the
end תוספות Tosafot says the following: so if you look down, you
look where, you see where it says ובעבודה זרה uve'avodah zarah in
the parentheses at the end of a line?
Everybody sees that? Do you see that like one, two, three, four,
five, six, like seven lines down in the narrow lines, in the,
no, Hanan you're in the wrong תוספות, Tosafot, it's ע"ב עמוד ב'.
Ayin Bet Amud Bet.
Okay, so he says there, if you go two lines below that,
he says אבל חולין בעזרה יהבי דרבנן וקידש בו את
האשה מקודשת וכך חשיב כפרי דאורייתא. aval chullin ba'azarah yehavi derabbanan vekiddesh
bo et ha'ishah mekuddeshet vekach chashiv kaprei de'oraita.
Okay. ומיהו איצטריך, umihu itztarich, so anyway, maybe I shouldn't have read
the תוספות Tosafot inside because it's too whatever, it's too embedded there.
But תוספות's Tosafot basic point is the following, is that it is
possible that something is אסור דרבנן asur derabbanan and it would have
a דאורייתא de'oraita implication, like you know, a certain type of rabbinic
חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach and so on. But here what the
גמרא Gemara means is that if it's אסור דרבנן, asur derabbanan, it's
not even אסור בהנאה. asur behana'ah. Okay, so back to the גמרא.
Gemara. So we got this problem. ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, Yeshnah
lishchitah mitechillah ve'ad sof, why are you חייב chayav four and five?
It says it must be חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is דרבנן. derabbanan.
ואי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא, Ve'ei salka da'atach de'oraita, if חולין בעזרה chullin
ba'azarah was דאורייתא de'oraita forbidden בהנאה, behana'ah, כי שחט בה פורתא אסרה,
ki shachat bah purta asrah, when you began the שחיטה, shchitah, you
made it דאורייתא de'oraita forbidden בהנאה. behana'ah. אידך לאו דמר קטבח. Idach
lav demare katavach. And then if you continued to שחט shachat it,
it no longer belonged to the owner. So again, same argument, it
must be, it must be
either you have to reject the position of ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד
סוף, yeshnah lishchitah mitechillah ve'ad sof, or here we have a new
answer. Fine, ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshnah lishchitah mitechillah ve'ad sof,
it becomes חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah at the beginning,
but it's only a דרבנן derabbanan status. Okay, it's not really אסור
בהנאה. asur behana'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא, Amar Rav
Acha berei deRava, no, כי קא מיחייב נהי דההוא פורתא. ki ka
michayev nehi de'hahu purta. No, no, no, we could say it's אסור
בהנאה asur behana'ah from the beginning of the process, but the beginning
of the process is also when you're חייב chayav for four and
five. So אמר ליה, amar leih, it's the same thing we said
before. אמר ליה רב אשי לא תדחיה, Amar leih Rav Ashi lo
tidcheih, don't push it off by saying that, oh, you're חייב chayav
four and five at the beginning. You can't say that. וטבחו כולו
בעינא וליכא, Utvacho kulo be'ina veleika, when it says and you slaughter
it, you have to slaughter the whole thing. You're only חייב chayav
four and five at the end of the process. So if you're
only חייב chayav four and five at the end, and the שחיטה
shchitah is at the beginning, and the שחיטה shchitah makes it אסור
בהנאה, asur behana'ah, we got a problem. So answer number one is,
you reject the idea that the שחיטה shchitah begins at the beginning.
Answer number two is, you reject the idea that it becomes אסור
בהנאה asur behana'ah at the beginning, that the status of חולין בעזרה
chullin ba'azarah is אסור בהנאה, asur behana'ah, we don't hold of that.
It's not דאורייתא, de'oraita, we don't hold of it at all that
it's אסור. asur. And here's answer number three, אמר ליה רב אשי,
amar leih Rav Ashi, so we just did that. אלא קשיא, Ella
kashya, so it's difficult. אמר ליה הכי אמר רב גמדא משמיה דרבא,
Amar leih hachi amar Rav Gamda mishmei deRava, כי קא מיחייב כגון
ששחט מקצת סימנים בחוץ וגמרן בפנים. ki ka michayev kegon sheshachat miktzat
simanim bachutz ugamran bifnim. The funny little story about walking the animal
in. Okay, no, here's a way in which you did the act
of חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah only at the end. You were walking
the animal in and only when you brought that last little bit
in, was it in the עזרה azarah and that's when you שחט-ed
shachat it. All right, very nice. So it's another application of this
question of whether the process of שחיטה shchitah starts at the beginning
or only starts at the end, with the גמרא Gemara saying that
when it comes to the חיוב chiyuv of four and five, that's
obviously
at the end, regardless of how you define the act of שחיטה
shchitah elsewhere. Okay, moving on now to the next משנה. Mishnah. All
right, the next משנה Mishnah gets us back to the question of
עדים. edim. Before we had a question of two עדים edim about
the גניבה geneivah and two עדים edim about the טביחה ומכירה, tvechah
umechirah, the question was דבר וחצי דבר, davar vechatzi davar, right, on
a full thing or a half thing. Now we turn to a
very central place of the גמרא's Gemara discussion about the idea of
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, because that's going to be the topic in
the משנה. Mishnah. Elsewhere where it talks about עדים זוממים edim zomemim
like in מכות, Makkot, it talks about assuming the עדים edim have
been found זוממים, zomemim, what punishment you give them. Or in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin it talks about עדים זוממים edim zomemim and it's the process
of the testimony the other witnesses give to make the first witnesses
זוממין, zomemin, like they say you were with us on such and
such a day and so on. This has to do, well we'll
see what this has to do with, but the focus is going
to be when do they become זוממים? zomemim? So let's take a
look. This is a real juicy סוגיא. sugya. Okay, so גנב על
פי שנים וטבח ומכר על פיהם, Ganav al pi shenayim vetavach umachar
al pihem, somebody stole on the testimony of two witnesses and then
he slaughtered or sold it on the testimony of the same witnesses.
ונמצאו זוממים, Venimtze'u zomemim, and it was discovered that those witnesses were
false witnesses. Now again, just to make it clear, okay, what means,
what does זוממים zomemim mean? It doesn't mean if you have one
hundred percent incontrovertible evidence that they were lying because I don't know
you had a videotape or something like that, okay, or I don't
know, let's say you had some proof that the cow had already
been sold somewhere else at the same time or whatever, okay, whatever
the case might be, they're not זוממים. zomemim. They're lying עדים, edim,
okay, they're contradicted עדים, edim, but they're not זוממים, zomemim, even if
it's incontrovertible. Let alone if what you have is two witnesses say,
you know, he slaughtered it on that day and two other witnesses
say no he didn't, he was with us on a... on an
overseas trip, you know, up in the air, whatever, with us that
day, so it's two contradictory testimonies, that's not זוממין. zomemin. Actually in
that case you throw out both testimonies because you don't know who
to believe. Okay, but my point is even if you knew absolute
evidence that they were that that what they said was false based
on some other type of concrete evidence, they wouldn't be זוממין. zomemin.
The only way they're זוממין zomemin is if two other witnesses come
and say you couldn't know what you're testifying about what happened that
day because you were with us somewhere else, עמנו הייתם באותו היום.
imanu heyitem b'oto hayom. So they're not testifying about the, key is,
they're not testifying about the facts, they're testifying about the witnesses. They're
saying you are, not now we can infer you're lying because I'm
saying that something else happened, I'm actually directly testifying about you that
you are lying. Okay, that that you have given false testimony. And
that's what makes them זוממין. zomemin. Now the question is even there,
why do you believe the latter ones over the former ones? One
way I think that's a helpful way of thinking about it, one
of the ראשונים rishonim say and תוספות tosfot sort of alludes to
this, is because if you're testifying directly about the person, there's a
way in which you would always be, it would be obvious you'd
be believed. Let's say ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon come and testify
something happened, and then לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda come and they
bring testimony that ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon were, I don't know,
relatives to the person they were testifying about, or they testify that
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon were גזלנים gazlanim and פסולי עדות. psulei
edut. Okay, so then you wouldn't say, oh well, why do you
believe לוי Levi and יהודה, Yehuda, believe ראובן Reuven and שמעון? Shimon?
Because ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon weren't testifying, you know, about the
things לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda were, right? ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon were testifying about the facts, and לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda
were testifying that they were פסולי עדות. psulei edut. Okay, so in
that case you would believe לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda and you
throw out the testimony. So this becomes one way of thinking about
it is, you know, it's like לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda when
you're saying to ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon you were with us,
well, we're not going against what you're explicitly, I mean, you are
sort of, when you say you saw something you're implicitly saying you
were there and whatever, but nevertheless what we're effectively doing is not
debating your, you know, your testimony, we're talking about your status. And
we're sort of talking about and invalidating you, and somehow that leads
to this idea that, I mean not leads to, but that's the,
you know, something along those lines is the explanation of the חידוש
chiddush that we believe the second כיתה kat of witnesses to say
that the first one was with them, and we throw out the
first, we believe the second, and not only do we throw out
the first testimony, but we apply the law of the תורה Torah
which is ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם. v'asitem lo ka'asher zamam. Right, we
punish them as they would have done to others. So there are
other situations in which we throw out the testimony, competing testimonies about
the facts, okay, or contradictory evidence, like here's a case the גמרא
Gemara has with contradictory evidence: I say ראובן, Reuven, you know, two
witnesses testify ראובן Reuven killed שמעון, Shimon, and the way the גמרא
Gemara describes it very colorfully, ובא הרוג ברגליו, u'va harug b'raglav, שמעון
Shimon shows up in court. Okay, so it's pretty clear the witnesses
are lying, alright, but nevertheless they're not עדים זוממין. edim zomemin. Alright,
עדים זוממין, edim zomemin, there are other cases we throw out the
testimony, but עדים זוממין edim zomemin is only when the other כיתה
kat says you couldn't know that, you were with us, and the
חידוש chiddush is you believe the second כיתה kat and you do
כאשר זמם. ka'asher zamam. Okay, so that's the case in the משנה.
Mishnah. So two witnesses say גנב וטבח ומכר, ganav v'tavach u'machar, two
other witnesses say you can't know any about of that, you were
with us that whole time, and then the first group pays four
and five to the owner, yes.
The פסולי עדות, psulei edut, so that's not זוממין, zomemin, right? If
the second group says you're פסולי עדות. psulei edut. If the second
group, that's not זוממין. zomemin. Then you throw out the testimony of
the first group, but it's not זוממין, zomemin, right. Right. Okay, so,
okay, משנה. Mishnah. גנב על פי שנים וטבח ומכר על פי שנים
אחרים. ganav al pi shenayim v'tavach u'machar al pi shenayim acherim. Now
let's say what group number one testified that that this person was,
stole the cow, and group number two testified that they slaughtered or
sold
it. אלו ואלו נמצאו זוממין elu v'elu nimtze'u zomemin and both groups
are now found to be witnesses זוממין, zomemin, because group number three
says all four of you were with us at that time. הראשונים
משלמין תשלומי כפל, harishonim meshalmin tashlumei kefel, the first group pays double,
והאחרונים משלמין תשלומי ג', v'ha'achronim meshalmin tashlumei gimmel, and the second group
pays three, right, because the second group when they testified,
their testimony would have added only three times more of the payment,
right? First group says you're גנב, ganav, so you have to pay
double. Second group says you שחטת shachatat it or you sold it,
so now you pay four and five, so the second group added
an additional three payments, right, additional three times of the payment. So
that's what, that's what they pay. Okay, נמצאו אחרונים זוממין, nimtze'u achronim
zomemin, now let's say only the second group was found זוממין. zomemin.
הוא משלם תשלומי כפל, hu meshalem tashlumei kefel, so we still believe
the first group, so therefore you're this first guy, it's still assumed
that this guy is a גנב ganav and he's going to pay
כפל kefel because the first testimony still stands, והם משלמים תשלומי ג',
v'hem meshalmim tashlumei gimmel, and the, but the second group is זוממין,
zomemin, they were trying to make this poor גנב ganav pay more
than he had to, so they pay three times to the גנב.
ganav. The גנב ganav pays two times to the owner, and they
pay three times to the גנב. ganav. Okay, אחד מן האחרונים echad
min ha'achronim Okay, היכא דאחרונים זוממין, eicha de'acharonim zommin, now let's say
only one of the last group is a זומם. zomem. Okay, they
only said to one of the guys in the last group, you
were with us. So if you take away one witness, that undermines
the entire testimony, but the principle of כאשר זמם ka'asher zomam is
only when both witnesses are זוממים. zomemim. Okay, so when you make
one witness a זומם, zomem, you void the testimony, but you don't
have the rule of כאשר זמם. ka'asher zomam. So, אחד מן האחרונים
זומם, echad min ha'acharonim zomem, if one of the last group is
a זומם, zomem, בטלה עדות שנייה, batla eidus shniya, you throw out
the second testimony, so the גנב ganav only pays double, but nobody
is paying the additional payments, right? The גנב ganav isn't because you
threw out the testimony, the witnesses aren't because they weren't both found
to be זוממים. zomemim. אחד מן הראשונים זומם, echad min harishonim zomem,
let's say one of the first ones is a זומם, zomem, so
בטלה כל העדות, batla kol haeidus, we throw out everything, right? Because
why? שאם אין גנבה אין טביחה ואין מכירה. she'im ein gneivah ein
tivichah ve'ein michirah. If you can't establish that the guy stole, you
know, or burgled it, then you're not going to pay the four
and five. So if you threw out the first testimony that he
was a גנב, ganav, the guy's not going to pay anything. Sure,
did I שחט shecht the animal? Of course I שחטed shecht it.
I'm going to claim that I bought it off of the owner.
All you know is that I שחטed shecht this animal that used
to belong to someone else. But we have no testimony that I
stole it. I'm going to say I owned it legitimately. Okay, so
therefore, if you throw out the testimony that I stole it, you
can't make me pay כפל, kefel, and nobody, the עדים eidim aren't
going to pay because none of them were, no group was found
to be זוממים. zomemim. So just everything gets thrown out and, you
know, and it's like nobody testified about anything. Okay, so that's the
case of the משנה. Mishna. Yes. Because you need two witnesses, right?
So if they're both testifying about the same evidence. Right. So how
is one a זומם zomem and not the other? Because ראובן ושמעון
Reuven veShimon say that on Tuesday at the you know 9:00 AM,
you know, so-and-so like stole this animal, and I say, ראובן, Reuven,
you can't say that, we were out playing baseball Tuesday at 9:00
AM. So only one, I've only about one of the two is
a זומם. zomem. So that's why one of them is a זומם.
zomem. That, you know, voided the whole group, but the group doesn't
become זוממים. zomemim. To be זוממים, zomemim, both of them have to
be, but that was enough to invalidate his testimony, but not enough
to apply the law of עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. Alright, okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אתמר, itmar,
it was taught,
עד זומם, eid zomem, what is the status of an עד זומם?
eid zomem? Meaning, when does a person become an עד זומם? eid
zomem? אביי אמר למפרע הוא נפסל. Abaye amar l'mafrei'a hu nifsul. So
basically, if somebody testified,
okay, a little timeline, okay, here's January 1,
okay,
March 1, and December 1. Okay, so here is where the two
witnesses are standing in court.
I don't know what I'm doing here. Okay, they're raising up their
hand, yes, I swear to tell the truth, the whole truth, okay,
whatever they are. Okay, here they're testifying, okay? And they're testifying that
an event occurred back here, okay? That here's where the guy did
the you know, here's where he was גנב וטבח ומכר, ganav vetavach
umachar, whatever they're saying happened back there. Okay, comes December 1, and
these other two witnesses say, I should have other colors, but okay,
whatever, and they say, up, you're זוממים, zomemim, you were with us.
Okay. Now, so had the case closed
already? What, well, yeah, I mean, yeah, you need a גמר דין
gmar din to be זומם. zomem. Okay, but anyway,
but yeah, you mean כאשר זמם ולא כאשר עשה, ka'asher zomam velo
ka'asher asah, let's not worry about that. It was a long court
case, lot of delays. Anyway, whatever. So the question is here,
let's make these guys into, let's make them different pictures. Okay, so
when did these two guys become פסול לעדות? pasul le'eidus? Let's say
they, after they gave this false testimony, which we now see in
hindsight was false, let's say they gave a lot of other testimony
in the middle here. They signed some שטרות, shtaros, they did a
lot of other good you know, a lot of other testifying. When
do they become false witnesses? So אביי Abaye said, well, now that
here we see that they were זוממים, zomemim, we now realize, the
Torah tells us to believe these later witnesses, so we now realize
that back here they were lying. If we realize that back here
they were lying, so they transgressed the prohibition of testifying falsely. So
somebody who testifies falsely and transgresses that prohibition becomes an invalid witness.
So they become invalid witnesses starting at March 1st. And any testimony
they gave from that time on has to get retroactively thrown out.
Okay, so we have to go back and see if they were
on any documents or whatever, and we have to throw it all
out. Because now, although we found out about it here, retroactively we
realize that they were bearing false testimony back here. Okay? Yes, is
that clear? Yeah. Yep. Okay. All right, so אביי אמר למפרע הוא
נפסל, Abaye amar l'mafrei'a hu nifsul, retroactive. רבא אמר מכאן ולהבא הוא
נפסל. Rava amar mikan ulehabah hu nifsul. No,
they only become... from invalidated from this point on. Okay?
So אביי Abaye אמר amar למפרע lemafrei הוא hu נפסל nifsal retroactively.
Now הוא hu שעתא sha'ata דאתיד de'atid הוי havei ליה lei רשע
rasha from the moment they testified falsely they are considered wicked, והתורה
vehatorah אמרה amrah אל al תשת tashet רשע rasha עד, ed, actually
the פסוק pasuk is אל al תשת tashet ידך yadcha עם im
רשע rasha להיות liyot עד ed חמס, chamas, but
we basically take out some words and say it means do not
have a רשע rasha be a witness. So since they transgressed the
prohibition of testifying falsely, that gives them a status of being רשעים,
resha'im, and that means even if, and the point here about saying
that they are רשע rasha means, it's not like we say that
everything they testified here we question its veracity. Maybe it was a
hundred percent true, but it's like if you're a קרוב, karov, it's
like if you're a relative. It doesn't matter if it's true. Because
your personal status is a רשע, rasha, the testimony has no weight
in court. So it's not like we say, "Oh, once you lied
here, you must lie about everything." That's not the point. Once you
lied here, you have a technical status of being a רשע, rasha,
and therefore, whether it's true or not true, everything you testified on
since then is invalid. Okay? So that's what אביי Abaye says. רבא
Rava אמר amar מכאן ולהבא mikan u'l'haba. נפסל, nifsal, only from this
point on. עדים זוממים Edim Zomemim חידוש chidush הוא. hu. The whole
thing is a חידוש. chidush. Why is the whole thing a חידוש?
chidush? דהא deha תרי trei ותרי utrei נינהו, ninhu, it's two against
two. מאי mai חזית chazit דציית detzayyat להני lehani ציית tzayyat להני?
lehani? Why do you listen to these guys? These guys say, "Oh,
you were with us at the baseball game." "No, we say we
were watching somebody steal a cow." So why do you believe these
over these? So the whole thing is a חידוש. chidush. הלכך hilkach
אין ein לך lecha בו bo אלא ela משעת mishat חידושו chidush
ואילך. ve'eylach.
Therefore, you only have the חידוש, chidush, therefore you only apply their
status from the time the תורה Torah sort of tells you that
they become עדים זוממים. Edim Zomemim So conceptually what they are saying
is, according to
אביי, Abaye, yes, everybody could agree that there's a חידוש chidush when
the תורה Torah says that you believe the latter people. But what
is the חידוש? chidush? אביי Abaye says the חידוש chidush is that
the תורה Torah is telling me to believe the veracity of what
they said, to believe that therefore they testified falsely. So by believing
the veracity of what they said and they testified falsely, so now
I know that these guys were bad witnesses going back here. רבא
Rava is saying that's not necessarily what the תורה Torah is saying.
I mean, one way you could say it is the תורה Torah
is telling you to believe in the veracity, but only to believe
in it from this point forward, not believe in it retroactively. Because
there's no reason to believe that they're more correct than these people.
So if you're going to believe in it,
believe in it moving forward, like accept that assertion moving forward. But
maybe an even sharper way to say it is, maybe the תורה
Torah isn't even telling you to believe that they're true and they're
false. The תורה Torah is just telling you this is a process
that gives these people the status of עדים זוממים. Edim Zomemim Okay?
We still don't know who's telling the truth and who's telling the
falsehood. But the way the procedure of the court says, in this
circumstance, these people are going to be the ones that are going
to be labeled the עדים זוממים Edim Zomemim and we're going to
do כאשר ka'asher זמם. zamam. Now that sounds like a real חידוש,
chidush, right? Because why would you go ahead and apply all these
punishments if the תורה Torah wasn't telling you to actually believe in
who's telling the truth. But there's an interesting question about עדים זוממים,
Edim Zomemim which is the big question about עדים זוממים Edim Zomemim.
is that the punishment does not meet the crime, right? It's כאשר
ka'asher זמם zamam ולא velo כאשר ka'asher עשה. asah. You're applying to
them what they intended to do, not even what they succeeded in
doing. So what's the logic of that? Why do they deserve that
punishment? So the רמב"ן Ramban points out something על al התורה, hatorah,
very important because there's a couple of פרשיות parshiyot right in the
same cluster in the תורה, Torah, like שופטים, Shoftim, where the תורה
Torah has punishments that seem to be outsized for the crime. Can
anybody think of any other punishments that are outsized for the crime?
Particularly in that area in the תורה? Torah? What's like a classic
one that we say, "Oh, the person didn't deserve it, but you
do it anyway"? Can anybody think?
Classic one we say that is בן ben סורר sorer ומורה, umoreh,
right? We say בן ben סורר sorer ומורה umoreh never occurred. Why
you gonna go ahead put this kid to death just because he
disobeyed his parents? Okay? The other two that are right there, now
both by עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim. and בן ben סורר sorer ומורה,
umoreh, the תורה Torah says וכל vechol ישראל yisrael ישמעו yishme'u וייראו.
veyira'u. So by saying וכל vechol ישראל yisrael ישמעו yishme'u וייראו, veyira'u,
it's basically saying maybe the, the רמב"ן Ramban makes this point, maybe
the person didn't deserve the punishment, but it is necessary from a
societal perspective to sort of stamp down on this and particularly because
these are acts that undermine the institutions of authority. Right? False testimony
in court, if people think they can get away with that, that
undermines the court system. Right? Rebelling against parental authority, okay, it's not
exactly our idea right now about parental authority to that degree, but
that institution, I mean that's the primary institution of authority, right? So
therefore, if people are going to do things that threaten these institutions,
you have to take a very harsh approach to make it a
very clear message: You do not mess with the courts, you do
not mess with
the...
No, it is close. It is... it is a זקן ממרא, Zaken
Mamre, okay? To... what? עגלה ערופה? Egla Arufa? No, I don't think
so. No, the two other two are זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre and
the case of the נביא שקר, Navi Sheker, okay? Because the זקן
ממרא, Zaken Mamre, right, is a case also undermining the authority of
the court in terms of the authority—as it's sort of not as
it's, you know, adjudicating cases, but it's sort of its, you know,
judicial role of like, you know, of like making decisions, you know,
the authority of who gets to decide what the תורה Torah means,
right? Somebody else was going around like, "Yeah, don't listen to them.
Here's what it means." And the other one is, you know, is
the נביא שקר Navi Sheker is ultimately undermining God's authority. And all
of those, you could say, you know, what did they do exactly?
The זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, he פסק paskened against the court, you're
going to put him to death. Anyway, so the רמב"ן Ramban says
in all of those cases, the real emphasis is not so much
that the sin deserved that punishment, but that the society deserves that
punishment and he has to be the one that suffers as a
result. But we have to protect these institutions. So anyway, the relevance
of that here is is that it's very consistent with רבא Rava's
idea of חידוש. Chidush. You know, חידוש Chidush is saying like, "This
is just what the תורה Torah says how we have to handle
this case even if to some..." Now, I was focusing on that
the punishment was outsize, but we're still going to assume that the
guy obviously did something wrong. Okay, it's a little bit different to
say we don't even know whether he did something wrong. But nevertheless,
like what רבא Rava is saying is to some degree even after
this, we don't really know they lied falsely. If we're going to
see it as they lied falsely, it's only going to be from
this point forward. But we're really not—we really can't say with confidence
even after this that, "Oh, now we know they lied falsely." So
one way of starting thinking about it is this process makes them
עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim, without necessarily establishing as a fact that they
actually were lying. Which again, to say it that way is a
little too—is a little stark, but the to some degree he's saying
like, "Okay, if we assume they're lying, it's only from this point
forward." Yes. So does that mean and then did they have that
status that they can never testify again? What? They could never testify
again as a...
I mean, I mean, a person can who is a רשע, Rasha,
just ask in general, like, you know, a person who is a
רשע Rasha can regain their status, right? I mean, the גמרא Gemara
sort of discusses what you would have to do. Like it's basically
a process of תשובה Teshuvah that's not just a תשובה Teshuvah between
you and God, but a תשובה Teshuvah that makes it clear to
us as a society that you really have in practice, like, mended
your ways. You know, it's actually quite interesting. The גמרא Gemara in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin discusses it because there's like to be forgiven for God,
you know, it's just between me and God and I really need
sincere remorse or whatever. But to be re-trusted by society, like the
גמרא Gemara says if somebody's a gambler, you know, it's sort of
like, you know, in like in AA or whatever, you know, they
say you gotta get out of all of those structures that like
pulled you back into that lifestyle. Right? So the גמרא Gemara sort
of says like if the guy was a gambler, he has to
like, you know, tear up all of throw out all of his
gambling, like, you know, equipment and he's got, you know, he's got
to do very practical things that we can actually be confident as
a society that they have changed. So, yes, it is possible to
regain your status. Okay? It's not like a permanent status. Okay. Yeah?
Sorry. No. Go ahead. But the testimony that—is the court now throwing
that out or not throwing it out or keeping them in that
movement? Here? No, so so this testimony we throw out, but anything
here because that's part of the הלכה Halakha of עדים זוממים eidim
zomemim, that what they testified is thrown out. But anything between this
and this, that's still good. Okay? Their personal status as עדים edim
זוממים zomemim and as פסול עדות Pasul Edut and also as a
personal status that's going to get them punished for what they did,
that applies moving forward. Okay? But one of the הלכות Halakhot of
making them עדים edim זוממים zomemim. is you throw out that original
testimony. Yeah. גנבא וזכה? Gannava Ve'zakha? What? גנבא וזכה? Gannava Ve'zakha? The
original case? Well, he wasn't a גנבא. Gannava. He wasn't a גנב.
Gannav. Right. Exactly. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't really—focusing on the עדים.
edim Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. But that intensifies your question why עדים edim
זוממים zomemim. is treated differently than other false witnesses because... Right, but
really the issue is at root is the authority of the court
and then you shouldn't apply that to someone else who's proven in
a different... Right,
but it's very hard under most cases, right, to know that somebody—I
mean it's very hard in general to prove a case of perjury,
right? I mean, I think so. Because that's not—it's not enough to
know somebody lied, you have to know they were intentional. Anyway, but
it's very hard in general to know somebody lied. Like the case
I gave that בא הרוג ברגליו, Ba Harug Beraglav, the murder victim
showed up, you know? But even there you say, "Well, we were
mistaken, it looked like him," or whatever. So, you know, in a
way the תורה Torah is—it doesn't exactly explain why it limits it
to this case, but it's like, you know, you can't because it's
such a harsh punishment, you have to sort of limit the scope
of when are you going to assert that you know that these
people are like, you know, have perjured and are עדים edim זוממים.
zomemim But you're right, in principle it shouldn't be limited to that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. That's one answer. איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, others say, רבא נמי כאביי סבירא ליה,
Rava nami k'Abaye sevira lei, רבא Rava also holds in principle like
אביי. Abaye. You're right, now we know retroactively they were lying, they
were פסול pasul from this point on, but אמר למפרע נפסל. amar
l'mafrea nifsul. So what's the difference then between their approaches? So הכא
היינו טעמא דרבא, hacha hainu taama d'Rava, here's the reasoning of רבא,
Rava, משום פסידא דלקוחות mishum pseida d'luchochos
because it's so unfair from everybody who purchased an item with a
bill of sale or who lent money with a שטר, shtar, and
they're going to get these people to testify, they're going to say,
hey, these guys must be good, I heard them testify in court,
the court trusts them. And now what you're going to do is
you're going to throw out every single testimony over all those intervening
months? So we can't allow that. Right? We have to say just
from a practical perspective that we can't, you know, everybody's always going
to be at risk that all their documents are retroactively going to
get thrown out because somebody's going to be found months later to
be an עד זומם. ed zomem. So we have to basically say
as a דרבנן d'rabbanan rule we're going to allow the testimony to
stand. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what
difference does it make within רבא Rava whether you say the reason
is חידוש chiddush or whether you say the reason is because of
פסידא דלקוחות. pseida d'luchochos. So the גמרא Gemara is going to give
some נפקא מינות, nafka minos, but the most obvious נפקא מינה nafka
mina it doesn't give and תוספות Tosafos gives them. You know what
the most obvious נפקא מינה nafka mina is? When it's not something
that's a monetary issue. Let's say in the intervening time they testified
that a woman, they were witnesses for a woman's marriage or witnesses
for a woman's divorce, right? Or witnesses that somebody, another somebody committed
an act of, was מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. Are you going to
say, well, we're going to keep, even though that technically is false,
we're going to keep the testimony? No, of course not. You know,
issues that deal with personal status, with applying punishments to other people,
obviously those testimonies if we really believe it's false from here we're
going to throw out. The idea of the answer פסידא דלקוחות pseida
d'luchochos means within the field of like civil documents, you know, we'll
keep those testimonies acceptable. Okay, so that's the most obvious answer which
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say, but תוספות Tosafos says. Take a look
at תוספות. Tosafos.
תוספות Tosafos says,
where's the
תוספות? Tosafos? Hold on. One minute. No. Wait,
maybe the previous תוספות? Tosafos?
Is it top?
I'll find the תוספות. Tosafos. Okay, anyway. Oh wait, maybe I see
it. Oh yeah yeah, look at תוספות אי נמי, Tosafos ei nami,
look at the bottom of the תוספות אי נמי. Tosafos ei nami.
So he says like this: about six lines before that תוספות Tosafos
is over. He says line starts with the word מצי. matzi. He
says ואם מצי למימר, v'im matzi l'meimar, איכא בינייהו לעניין דיני נפשות,
ika beinaihu l'inyan dinei nefashos, let's say in the interim they testified
that somebody was חייב מיתה. chayav misa. We wouldn't keep it if
we really think they were false retroactively. או אשה לבעלה, o isha
l'baalah, or a woman that committed adultery. ולעניין גיטין וקידושין ועדות החודש.
u'l'inyan Gittin v'Kidushin v'eidus hachodesh. Anything that's not a civil document we
obviously are not going to keep because of a תקנה takana if
we really believe it was false. Okay, so there's a lot of
good answers that the גמרא Gemara could have said. But now the
גמרא Gemara is going to give a נפקא מינה nafka mina even
within the realm of civil documents. Is the reason we say from
here on because it's a חידוש chiddush or because we're trying to
protect innocent
people? So we're going to keep the civil documents even though they
really should be thrown out. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו,
mai beinaihu, what is the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says the
following: דאתי בי תרי לחד ובי תרי לחד. d'asi bei srei l'chad
u'bei srei l'chad. The difference would be two witnesses say this guy
was with them and two other witnesses say this guy was with
them. So in that case it's not a חידוש chiddush because in
that case it's two against one. Right? You get that? The חידוש
chiddush here is that it's two against two. If you say, so
oh, that's a חידוש, chiddush, so it should only be מכאן ולהבא.
mikan u'l'haba But let's say these two said only one guy was
with them and two other witnesses say the other guy was with
them. So in each one it's two against one, so it's not
a חידוש. chiddush. So in that case, if the only reason it
was מכאן ולהבא mikan u'l'haba, was because it was a חידוש, chiddush,
this wouldn't be a חידוש chiddush and it would be retroactive. But
if it's to protect the innocent לקוחות, luchochos, we're going to still
protect them. Okay, אי נמי, ei nami, or another way is דפסלינו
בגזלנותא, d'paslinu b'gazlanusa, what I said before. They said that they were
not with us on that day, they said, oh, these two are
גזלנים. gazlanim. That's not seen as a חידוש. chiddush. That's seen as
you're just testifying to that person's personal status and you do without
a חידוש chiddush you would naturally believe the later witnesses. ולהאי לישנא
דאמרת משום חידוש, u'l'hai lishna d'amrat mishum chiddush, according to the approach
that says that the only reason that the whole that you believe
the latter ones is a חידוש chiddush and therefore it's only מכאן
ולהבא, mikan u'l'haba. so in this case
ליכא, leka, there's not a חידוש chiddush here. There's a reason to
believe the latter ones and therefore it would apply retroactively. But להאי
לישנא דאמרת משום פסידא דלקוחות, l'hai lishna d'amrat mishum pseida d'luchochos, for
the one that says in principle it is retroactive but we need
to protect those innocent, you know, buyers and sellers and creditors and
so on, so איכא, ika, so All along we were admitting it
should have been retroactive. It doesn't matter that it's not a חידוש,
Chiddush, it should be retroactive, but we have to protect all of
those buyers and sellers, so therefore we're only going to say מכאן
ולהבא. mikan u'l'haba Okay. גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ירמיה מדפתי, Amar
Rav Yirmiya mi'Difti, עבד רב פפא עובדא כוותיה דרבא. avad Rav Pappa
uvda k'vasei d'Rava. רב פפא Rav Pappa acted like רבא Rava and
he basically made them פסול pasul only from the time that they
were זוממים zomemim, going forward. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, הלכתא
כוותיה דאביי, hilchasa k'vasei d'Abaye, no, we rule like אביי, Abaye, they're
פסול pasul retroactively. And the גמרא Gemara concludes,
והלכתא כוותיה דאביי ביע"ל קג"ם. v'hilchasa k'vasei d'Abaye b'Ya'al Kagam. This is
a mnemonic of the cases we rule like אביי, Abaye, and which
one do you think stands for our case?
עין, Ayin, עדים edim זוממים. zomemim Okay, so עין Ayin is the
עדים edim זוממים, zomemim let's see if I remember what the others
are, the למד Lamed is לחי העומד מאליו. Lechi ha-omed me-elav.
One of them, oh, the יוד Yud is יאוש שלא מדעת. Yeush
she-lo m'da'as. The קוף Kuf is... oh now I'm not remembering them.
Okay, anyway, whatever it is. What are the others?
Okay. קידושין שלא נמסרו לביאה, Kiddushin she-lo nimseru l'via, right. And the
גימל Gimmel is
גילוי מילתא בגיטא. Giluy milsa b'gita. And the מם? Mem? Oh, the
מם Mem is מומר אוכל נבילות לתיאבון. mumar ochel neveilos l'teiavon. Okay,
very good, יישר כח. shkayach. All right, anyway, so those are the
cases we rule like אביי. Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to continue with this debate even though we know how it concludes,
but this is really a fascinating debate about when does it become
invalid. One answer of לקוחות l'kuchos is an interest... it's always interesting
to see חז"ל Chazal just taking practical steps to protect the normal
runnings of society. Okay, but that, but that's not as conceptually interesting,
that would be limited to civil documents, not others. But the other
position of רבא, Rava, מכאן mikan ולהבא ulehaba is quite fascinating, saying
that this whole thing we, at the end of the day, we
don't really know that they're lying, the תורה Torah tells us to
treat them as if they're lying, and that we will only apply
moving forward, not
retroactively. Quite a radical way of thinking of עדים Edim. זוממים, zomemim
and we will continue working on this tomorrow. Okay.